Guide to the W. D. Davies papers, 1911-2007 UA.29.02.0016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
W. D. Davies papers
1911-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Davies, W. D. (William David), 1911-2001
UA.29.02.0016
106.5 Linear Feet 78 containers
W. D. (William David) Davies (1911-2001) was Professor of Biblical Theology at Duke University Divinity School from 1950 to 1955 and from 1966 to 1981 was George Washington Ivey Professor of Advanced Studies and Research in Christian Origins. The collection features correspondence, course materials, writings, subject files, sermon notes, books, and research notes of W. D. Davies. Major research subjects include the New Testament, especially Pauline letters; Christian theology; Judaism; and the issue of territorial imperative with regard to land.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The W. D. Davies papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1984-2001, and a gift in 2014.
Biographical/Historical note
W. D. (William David) Davies was born in Carmarthenshire, Wales, United Kingdom, and educated at the University of Wales (B.A.from Cardiff, 1934; B.D. from Breccon, 1938) and Cambridge University (B.A. 1940, M.A. 1942). Davies received his doctorate (D.D. operis causa 1948) from the University of Wales.
In 1941, Davies was ordained into the Congregational Church at Fowlmere, England. He taught at Yorkshire United College, Bradford, Yorkshire, from 1946 to 1950 before moving to Duke for five years as a professor of Biblical theology (1950 to 1955). From 1955 through 1959 he was professor of religion at Princeton University, where he helped start the graduate program in Religion. He was then appointed Edward Robinson Professor of Biblical Theology at Union Theological Seminary in New York, as well as adjunct professor at Columbia University, from 1959 to 1966. He rejoined the Duke faculty in 1966 as George Washington Ivey Professor of Advanced Studies and Research in Christian Origins. He stayed until his retirement in 1981. He then became the Bradford Professor at Texas Christian University in Fort Worth, Texas and in 1986-87 he was a Fellow of Clare Hall, Cambridge, UK. He also taught at the University of California at Berkeley (1971-1972) and at the University of Strasboroug, France (1973-1974).
Davies held numerous fellowships and received several awards and honors. He was a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, a Corresponding Fellow of the British Academy, (from which he also received the Burkitt Medal in Biblical Studies in 1965), an Honorary Fellow of Cambridge University's Fitzwilliam College, a Fellow of the Bellagio Center, Italy, and Fellow of the American Academy of Jewish Research. He was a recipient of two Guggenheim Fellowships and received honorary doctorates from the University of St. Andrews, the Pacific School of Religion, Uppsala University and the University of Wales, the latter being an honorary doctorate in literature. Davies also served as honorary president of the Society for Biblical Literature and President of the Society of New Testament Studies (1976), which met in the United States for the first time that year at Duke University. He was a member of the executive committee of the World Congress of Jewish Studies, Jerusalem (1965).
Among his published works are the Paul and Rabbinic Judaism (1948), the The Setting of the Sermon on the Mount (1966), and the The Gospel and the Land: Early Christianity and Jewish Territorial Doctrine (1974). His popular the Invitation to the New Testament (1966) was a selection of the Book of the Month Club. He was also co-editor of the the Cambridge History of Judaism and along with a former student published an International Critical Commentary on Matthew (3 vols).
W.D. Davies married Eurwen Llewelyn in 1942 in Wales. The couple had one daughter, Rachel M. Davies. W.D. Davies died June 12, 2001 in Durham, NC, and Eurwen L. Davies died on January 16, 2002.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, research materials, teaching materials, photographs, and books. Major research subjects include the New Testament, especially Pauline letters; Christian theology; Judaism; and the issue of territorial imperative with regard to land.
The first series, containing multiple accessions, includes correspondence, manuscript materials, article reprints, student papers, lecture notes, course reading materials, sermon notes, student notebooks relating to courses taken at the University of Wales Memorial College in Brecon, general research subject files, research notes relating to teaching at Duke University, Columbia University, Princeton University, Union Theological Seminary, and Texas Christian University.
Accession UA2014-0065 contains personal and professional correspondence, scholarly materials and books from Davies' personal library. The collection also contains materials related to Davies' Feschrift, an honor celebrating Davies'contributions to the field of biblical theology.
Related Material
Divinity School records, 1925-2005.
University Archives. Duke University.
Bible. N.T. -- Introductions; Bible. N.T. -- Criticism, interpretation, etc.; Bible -- Theology -- History of doctrines; Bible -- Theology -- Study and teaching; Church -- Sermons; Congregational Church in England and Wales -- Clergy; Education (Christian theology); Judaism -- History -- Post-exile period, 586 B.C.-210 A.D.; Judaism -- Relations -- Christianity; Palestine in the Bible; Palestine in Christianity -- History of doctrines -- Early church, ca. 30-600 A.D.; Palestine in Judaism; Religion -- Study and teaching; Sermon on the Mount -- Criticism, interpretation, etc.; Bible -- Epistles of Paul -- Theology; Bible -- Epistles of Paul -- Study and teaching; Land settlement -- Palestine; Duke University. Divinity School; Davies, W. D. (William David), 1911-2001; Duke University -- Faculty
- Accessions A84-35, A89-70, A90-102, A92-94, A2001-21, 51 boxes
  - The Gospel and the Land: drafts, notes (Box 1)
  - Jerusalem and the Land in the Christian tradition: drafts, notes (Box 2)
  - The Jewish State in the Hellenistic World (Box 2)
  - The Territorial Dimension of Judaism (Box 2)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Course materials, 1967 (Box 3)
  - General research: Judeo-Christian relations (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous sermon and lecture notes (Box 4)
  - Lecture notes (Box 5)
  - Student papers (Box 5)
  - Pantyfedwen Lecture (Wales), 1968 (Box 5)
  - Paul and the Law (Box 5)
  - The New Creation (sermon collection) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous lecture notes (Box 6)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism (CHJ) (Box 7)
  - Personal and professional correspondence, arranged by date (Box 8)
  - Sermons preached in Fowlmere, England, 1941-1946 (Box 9)
  - Kearns Lecture, Duke University, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, volume 1 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous research articles in Italian (Box 10)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1978 (A89-70) (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - People/project files (A-G) (Box 13)
  - Vita, 1986 (Box 13)
  - People/project files (H-P) (Box 14)
  - People/project files (Q-Z) (Box 15)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 16)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, 1980-1986 (Box 17)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, 1981-1988 (Box 18)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, volumes I-II (Box 19)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, volumes III-IV (Box 20)
  - Pirké Aboth (Box 21)
  - Territorial Imperative (Box 21)
  - Holy Land Colloquium, 1975 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues) (Box 21)
  - David Daube writings (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 22)
  - NEH Seminar information and applications, 1982 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues) (Box 23)
  - Student papers, ca 1960-1986 (Box 23)
  - General research subject files (bulk 1973-1974) (Box 24)
  - University Research Council (Box 24)
  - Travel expenses (Box 24)
  - Grants, 1981-1982 (Box 24)
  - Course outlines (Box 25)
  - General research subject files, bulk 1973-1974 (Box 25)
  - Personal files ("from desk") (Box 26)
  - General research subject files (Box 26)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, ca 1967 (Box 27)
  - Sermon notes (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Box 27)
  - Lecture notes (Box 28)
  - Sermon notes (Box 28)
  - Reprints (Box 28)
  - Paul, Pauline doctrine (Box 29)
  - Mormonism (Box 29)
  - Lecture notes (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): A-B (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): C-Di (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): Do-G (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): H-K (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): L-M (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): Sch-St (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): St-W (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous reprints (Box 37)
  - Course teaching notes (Box 38)
  - Introduction to Theory (Box 38)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, volumes II-IV (Box 39)
  - International Critical Commentary, volume II (Box 39)
  - International Critical Commentary, volumes I-II (Box 40)
  - Book reviews of works by W.D. Davies (Box 41)
  - Details of appointments at Duke, Berkeley, and Princeton (Box 41)
  - Conference and lecture notes (Box 41)
  - Commentary on Matthew (Box 42)
  - Japan correspondence (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 42)
  - International Critical Commentary on Matthew, galley proofs (Box 43)
  - Student notebooks (at Brecon), ca 1930 (Box 44)
  - Student notebooks (at Brecon), ca 1930 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence P-Sch (Box 46)
  - Correpsondence N-O (Box 47)
  - Torah Min Hashamayim by Abraham Joshua Heschel (Box 48)
  - Society of Biblical Literature certificate, 1976 (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (mostly 1996-1997) (Box 48)
  - Draft of Reflections on Aspects of the Jewish Background of the Gospel of John (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous writings and correspondence (mostly 1996-1997) (Box 49)
  - Article reprints (Box 49)
  - Sermon at Princeton University, 1985 (Box 49)
  - Bibliography (Box 49)
  - Mystical Antisemitism (Box 49)
  - Reviews of Cambridge History of Judaism, edited by W.D. Davies and Louis Finkelstein (Box 49)
  - The Shroud of Turin (by colleagues) (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous reprints (Box 50)
  - Correspondence (mostly 1992-1993) (Box 50)
  - Reflections of Judaism (Box 50)
  - Contemporary Quest for the Historical Jesus (Box 50)
  - Framed photographs (Box 50)
  - Reprints, 1995 (Box 50)
  - Compositional History of Q, draft (Box 51)
  - Paul and the New Exodus (Box 51)
  - Reflections on Aspects of the Jewish Background of the Gospel of John (Box 51)
  - Then and There (Box 51)
  - The Jewish Sources of Matthew's Messianism (Box 51)
  - The Intertextual Jesus: Scripture in Q (Box 51)
- Accession UA2014.0065, 1911-2007; 2
  Scope and Contents
  Accession UA2014-0065 contains correspondence, notes, manuscript drafts, lecture materials, photographs, and books created or collected by Duke Professor W.D. Davies. Much of the material in this collection dates from the end of Davies' tenure at Duke and his later retirement in Durham.
  This series features the Correspondence subseries which contain personal and professional correspondece between Davies and friends, acquantainces, and scholarly collaborators. Correspondence also include Davies' Feschrift, a collection of essays written in his honor to celebrate his contributions to the field of biblical theology. The series also contains the Scholarly Materials subseries which includes manuscript drafts, publication notes, source lists and other materials used in the creation of his books and journal articles. The Family Materials subseries includes materials related to both W.D. and Eurwen Davies and their deaths. Also included are many of W.D. Davies' books.
  - Correspondence: Personal, 1
    The Personal Correspondence subseries contains communications between W.D. Davies and his friends and colleagues. Correspondents include prominent biblical scholars such as C.H. Dodd, J.S. Whale, legal scholar and close friend David Daube, and theologian Reinhold Neibuhr, and as well as Duke University French professor Wallace Fowlie. Correspondence provides insight into his scholarly and personal life.
    Some personal correspondence is restricted and requires the permission of Rachel M. Davies to access. Contact Research Services for more information.
    This series is organized alphabetically by correspondent.
    - Kenneth Cragg; Jean Chevallier; Martin Hengel; R. Lowe, 1966-2000 (Box 52)
    - Oscar Cullman, 1967-1995 (Box 52)
    - David Daube, 1956-2000; 2 folders (Box 52)
    - A.O. Davies, 1961-1981 (Box 52)
    - C.H. Dodd and family, 1951-1997 (Box 52)
    - Gwynvor Evans and other Welshmen, 1966-1998 (Box 52)
    - Joel Fleishman; Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, 1987-2000 (Box 52)
    - Wallace Fowlie, 1966-1995 (Box 52)
    - Reinhold Neibuhr and family, 1971-1996 (Box 52)
    - Bishop John Robinson, 1983-1984 (Box 52)
    - Marcel Simon (French), 1976-1991 (Box 52)
    - J.S. Whale, 1957-1997; 3 folders (Box 52)
    - Amos Wilder, 1972;1975;1993 (Box 52)
    - Former Students, 1961-2000 (Box 52)
    - Cambridge University, 1975-1998 (Box 52)
    - University of Strasbourg, 1986-2001 (Box 52)
    - Misc Correspondence, 1969-2000 (Box 52)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1991 (Box 52)
    - Restricted Correspondence, 1965-1996 (Box 61)
  - Correspondence: Professional, 2
    The Professional Correspondence subseries contains communications relating to the development of W.D. Davies' work. Correspondents include publishers such as Cambridge University Press, Trinity University Press and Midstream magazine and co-authors such as Dale Allison.
    - Cambridge University Press, 1990-2000 (Box 52)
    - Cambridge History of Judaism Volume III, 1985-1999 (Box 52)
    - Christian Origin and Judaism, 1997-2000 (Box 52)
    - Conferences and Publications, 1990-1993 (Box 52)
    - Duke, 1966-1986 (Box 52)
    - Later Professional Correspondence, 1966;1982-2001; 3 folders (Box 52)
    - Professional Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box 52)
    - Trinity Press, 1996-1999 (Box 52)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1996-1997 (Box 52)
    - Writings in Retirement, 1990-2000 (Box 52)
  - Scholarly Materials, 3
    The Scholarly Materials subseries contains materials related to the creation of articles, books and lectures. Materials include manuscript drafts, notes, and lists of books and articles Davies' used as references. Manuscript drafts include Davies' collaboration with Dale Allison on a three volume commentary on the apostle Matthew.
    The series also includes four audio-cassette tapes of a lecture Davies gave on the apostle Paul in Strasbourg and four floppy disks containing drafts of Davies' work.
    - Dale Allison (1-2 of 3), 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 52)
    - Dale Allison (3 of 3), 1992 (Box 53)
    - Feschrift Letters, 1975-1976 (Box 53)
    - Feschrift Scroll, 1975-1976 (Box 58)
    - Off-Prints, 1981-1985 (Box 53)
    - Lecture Materials, 1992 (Box 53)
    - Manuscript: Commentary on Matthew, 1996 (Box 53)
    - Matthew Manuscript, undated (Box 53)
    - Midstream, 1987-1998 (Box 53)
    - Mystical Anti-semitism files, 1994-1995 (Box 54, Disk UA29-02-0016-FL5-0002)
    - Mystical Anti-semitism files, 1995 (Box 54, Disk UA29-02-0016-FL3-0002)
    - Scholarly Misc, 1986-2001; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Scholarly Reference Materials, 1948-2000; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1968 (Box 53)
    - Off-Prints (1-4 of 5), 1953-2007; 4 folders (Box 53)
    - Off-Prints (5 of 5), 1960-1997 (Box 54)
    - Reprints by W.D. Davies and others, 1977-1998 (Box 55)
    - Sermon Notebooks, 1941-1947 (Box 54)
    - Doctrine of Grace notebook, circa 1937 (Box 55)
    - Bellagio, 1980-1983 (Box 54)
    - Honors, 1941-1986 (Box 54)
    - Honors, awards, and honorary degrees, 1953-1980 (Box 56)
    - W.D. Davies degrees and certificates, 1929-1944 (Box 77)
    - Clippings and Misc, 1925-2001 (Box 54)
    - Bradford Chair Celebration, Texas Christian University, 1983 (Box 54)
    - Reflections on the Sermon on the Mount, undated (Box 54)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1986-1997; 4 folders (Box 54)
    - Computer back-up and text files, 1993-1994 (Box 54, Disk UA29-02-0016-FL5-0001)
    - Computer back-up and text files, 1994-1997 (Box 54, Disk UA29-02-0016-FL3-0001)
    - Cambridge History of Judaism Volume III, 1982, undated (Box 56)
    - Cambridge History of Judaism Volume IV, 1979, 1985, undated (Box 56)
    - SNTS Seminar (Durham, NC), 1972-1976 (Box 56)
    - Scholarly Misc, 1992-2001 (Box 56)
    - References to Books on Judaism, undated (Box 56)
    - Torah and Modern Life in Israel, 1958 (Box 56)
    - Uppsala University (Sweden) honorary degree hat, 1974 (Box 59)
    - Event poster, honors, awards, and certificates, 1949-1990 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Family Materials, 4
    This series includes materials of a personal nature related to W.D. and Eurwen Davies and their family. Included are personal writings, photographs, passports and birth certificates, and letters of condolence after the deaths of W.D. and Eurwen Davies.
    - Personal Writings, undated (Box 52)
    - Eurwen Llewelyn Davies Writings, 1951-1953 (Box 52)
    - Photographs of W.D. and Eurwen Llewelyn Davies, undated (Box 77)
    - Photographs of Rachel M. Davies, undated (Box 77)
    - Photos, undated; 5 folders (Box 54)
    - Group photographs, undated (Box 77)
    - Photo album, 1976 (Box 57)
      Photos taken at the Durham, NC meeting of the Society of New Testament Studies. Compiled into an album by Rachel M. Davies.
    - Divinity News and Notes, Spring and Fall 2001 (Box 56)
    - W.D. and Eurwen Llewelyn Davies 50th wedding anniversary materials, 1991-1992; 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Letters of condolence on death of W.D. Davies (1 of 3), 2001 (Box 54)
    - Letters of condolence on death of W.D. Davies (2-3 of 3), 2001; 2 folders (Box 55)
    - W.D. Davies memorial service guest book, 2001; 2 folders (Box 55)
    - W.D. Davies obituaries and death notices, 2001 (Box 55)
    - "In Long Measure: for W.D. Davies" by Reynolds Price, June 24, 2001 (Box 55)
      Eulogy delivered at Duke University Chapel.
    - Letters of condolence and materials on death of Eurwen Llewelyn Davies, 2002; 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Eurwen Llewelyn Davies degrees, awards, and certificates, 1928-1965 (Box 77)
    - W.D. and Eurwen Llewelyn Davies birth certificates, marriage license, citizenship papers, and re-entry permits, 1911-1972 (Box 55)
    - W.D. Davies passports, 1950-1994 (Box 55)
    - Eurwen Llewelyn Davies passports, 1950-1994 (Box 55)
    - Address book/rolodex cards, undated; 3 folders (Box 55)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 60)
  - Books, 5
    - Abraham Geiger and the Jewish Jesus, 1998 (Box 68)
      Author: Susannah Heschel; Publisher: The University of Chicago Press; Place of Publication: Chicago; Paperback; Language: English; Significance to W.D. Davies: Inscription, Annotated
    - Ac Onide, 1970 (Box 69)
      Author: J.R. Jones; Publisher: Merlin Press; Place of Publication: Sir Gaerfryrddin; Hardcover; Language: Welsh; Significance to W.D. Davies: Inscription
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Records and Directory, 2001 (Box 76)
      Publisher: American Academy of Arts and Sciences; Place of Publication: Cambridge; Paperback; Language: English
    - American Jewry and the Arts, 1987 (Box 73)
      Author: Jacob Neusner; Publisher: The National Foundation for Jewish Culture; Place of Publication: New York; Paperback; Language: English
    - Ancient Israel: A Short History from Abraham to the Roman Destruction of the Temple, 1988 (Box 68)
      Author: Herschel Shanks; Publisher: Biblical Archeology Society; Place of Publication: Washington DC; Hardcover; Language: English; Significance to W.D. Davies: Inscription
    - The Ancient Library of Qumran, 1995 (Box 71)
      Author: Frank Moore Cross; Publisher: Fortress Press; Place of Publication: Minneapolis; Paperback; Language: English; Third edition
    - Anti-Semite and Jew, 1966 (Box 70)
      Author: Jean-Paul Sartre; Publisher: Shocken Books; Place of Publication: New York; Paperback; Language: English
    - Anti-Semitism in the Ancient World, 1986 (Box 76)
      Author: Louis H. Feldman; Publisher: The Jewish Publication Society; Place of Publication: Philadelphia; Paperback; Language: English
    - The Apocryphal Old Testament, 1984 (Box 71)
      Author: H.F.D. Sparks; Publisher: Oxford University Press; Place of Publication: New York; Hardcover; Language: English; Edited by H.F.D. Sparks
    - Aproximacion Al Nuevo Testamento, 1979 (Box 62)
      Author: W.D. Davies; Place of Publication: Madrid; Paperback; Language: Spanish; translated by J. Valiente Malla; Significance to W.D. Davies: Authored
    - Ar Drywydd Y Mormoniaid, 1999 (Box 72)
      Author: Geraint Bowen; Publisher: Gomer Press; Place of Publication: Llandysul; Paperback; Language: Welsh
    - Arab and Jew: Wounded Sprits in a Promised Land, 1986 (Box 70)
      Author: David K. Shipler; Publisher: Penguin Books; Place of Publication: New York; Paperback; Language: English
    - Atlas of the Bible (Box 75)
      Author: John Rogerson; Language: English
    - Awdlau Cadeiriol Detholedig Y Ganrif Hon, 1930 (Box 72)
      Author: Syr John Morris-Jones; Place of Publication: London; Hardcover; Language: Welsh
    - The Background of the New Testament and Its Eschatology: Studies In Honor of C.H. Dodd, 1956 (Box 63)
      Author: Co-edited by W.D. Davies and David Daube; Publisher: Cambridge University Press; Place of Publication: New York; Hardcover; Language: English, French, German; Significance to W.D. Davies: Co-editor, Annotated
    - The Background of the New Testament and Its Eschatology: Studies In Honor of C.H. Dodd, 1964 (Box 65)
      Author: Co-edited by W.D. Davies and D. Daube; Publisher: Cambridge University Press; Place of Publication: New York; Hardcover; Language: English; Significance to W.D. Davies: Co-editor
    - The Background of the New Testament and Its Eschatology: Studies In Honor of C.H. Dodd, 1964 (Box 65)
      Author: Co-edited by W.D. Davies and D. Daube; Publisher: Cambridge University Press; Place of Publication: New York; Paperback; Language: English; Significance to W.D. Davies: Co-editor
    - Bergs Pre Dikan, 1971 (Box 62)
      Author: W.D. Davies; Publisher: Cambridge University Press; Place of Publication: Stockholm, Sweden; Paperback; Language: Swedish; translated by Stig Lindhagen; Significance to W.D. Davies: Authored
    - Between God and Man: An Interpretation of Judaism (Box 74)
      From the Writings of Abraham J. Heschel, edited by Fritz A. Rothschild; Language: English
    - The Bible in Modern Scholarship, 1965 (Box 67)
      Author: J. Philip Hyatt; Publisher: Abingdon Press; Place of Publication: Nashville, Tennessee; Hardcover; Language: English; Significance to W.D. Davies: Contributor